approximately 50,000 to 70,000 people, who live in this community of self-built multi-story houses where up to three generations live in one structure. While these apartments that they built for themselves appear to lack any planning or formal grid, each family specializing in a certain form of recycling means that the ground floor of each apartment is reserved for garbage-related activities and the upper floor is dedicated to living space. I find it incredible to see how these piles and piles of garbage are invisible to the people who live there, like this very distinguished man who is posing while all this garbage is sort of streaming out behind him, or like these two young men who are sitting and chatting amongst these tons of garbage. While to most of us, living amongst these piles and piles of garbage may seem totally uninhabitable, to those in the Zabbaleen, this is just a different type of normal. In all these places I've talked about today, what I do find fascinating is that there's really no such thing as normal, and it proves that people are able to adapt to any kind of situation. Throughout the day, it's quite common to come across a small party taking place in the streets, just like this engagement party. In this tradition, the bride-to-be displays all of their belongings, which they soon bring to their new husband. A gathering like this one offers such a juxtaposition where all the new stuff is displayed and all the garbage is used as props to display all their new home accessories. Like Makoko and the Torre David, throughout the Zabbaleen you'll find all the same facilities as in any typical neighborhood. There are the retail shops, the cafes and the restaurants, and the community is this community of Coptic Christians, so you'll also find a church, along with the scores of religious iconographies throughout the area, and also all the everyday services like the electronic repair shops, the barbers, everything. Visiting the homes of the Zabbaleen is also full of surprises. While from the outside, these homes look like any other informal structure in the city, when you step inside, you are met with all manner of design decisions and interior decoration. Despite having limited access to space and money, the homes in the area are designed with care and detail. Every apartment is unique, and this individuality tells a story about each family's circumstances and values. Many of these people take their homes and interior spaces very seriously, putting a lot of work and care into the details. The shared spaces are also treated in the same manner, where walls are decorated in faux marble patterns. But despite this elaborate decor, sometimes these apartments are used in very unexpected ways, like this home which caught my attention while all the mud and the grass was literally seeping out under the front door. When I was let in, it appeared that this fifth-floor apartment was being transformed into a complete animal farm, where six or seven cows stood grazing in what otherwise would be the living room. But then in the apartment across the hall from this cow shed lives a newly married couple in what locals describe as one of the nicest apartments in the area. The attention to this detail astonished me, and as the owner of the home so proudly led me around this apartment, from floor to ceiling, every part was decorated. But if it weren't for the strangely familiar stomach-churning odor that constantly passes through the apartment, it would be easy to forget that you are standing next to a cow shed and on top of a landfill. What moved me the most was that despite these seemingly inhospitable conditions, I was welcomed with open arms into a home that was made with love, care, and unreserved passion. Let's move across the map to China, to an area called Shanxi, Henan and Gansu. In a region famous for the soft, porous Loess Plateau soil, there lived until recently an estimated 40 million people in these houses underground. These dwellings are called the yaodongs. Through this architecture by subtraction, these yaodongs are built literally inside of the soil. In these villages, you see an entirely altered landscape, and hidden behind these mounds of dirt are these square, rectangular houses which sit seven meters below the ground. When I asked people why they were digging their houses from the ground, they simply replied that they are poor wheat and apple farmers who didn't have the money to buy materials, and this digging out was their most logical form of living. From Makoko to Zabbaleen, these communities have approached the tasks of planning, design and management of their communities and neighborhoods in ways that respond specifically to their environment and circumstances. Created by these very people who live, work and play in these particular spaces, these neighborhoods are intuitively designed to make the most of their circumstances. In most of these places, the government is completely absent, leaving inhabitants with no choice but to reappropriate found materials, and while these communities are highly disadvantaged, they do present examples of brilliant forms of ingenuity, and prove that indeed we have the ability to adapt to all manner of circumstances. What makes places like the Torre David particularly remarkable is this sort of skeleton framework where people can have a foundation where they can tap into. Now imagine what these already ingenious communities could create themselves, and how highly particular their solutions would be, if they were given the basic infrastructures that they could tap into. Today, you see these large residential development projects which offer cookie-cutter housing solutions to massive amounts of people. From China to Brazil, these projects attempt to provide as many houses as possible, but they're completely generic and simply do not work as an answer to the individual needs of the people. I would like to end with a quote from a friend of mine and a source of inspiration, Zita Cobb, the founder of the wonderful Shorefast Foundation, based out of Fogo Island, Newfoundland. She says that "there's this plague of sameness which is killing the human joy," and I couldn't agree with her more. Thank you. (Applause)
aproximadamente entre 50 y 70 mil personas, que viven en esta comunidad de edificios de varias plantas construidos por ellos mismos donde hasta tres generaciones viven en una estructura. Mientras que estas viviendas que construyen ellos mismos carecen aparentemente de planificación o diseño formal, el que cada familia se especialice en una forma de reciclaje significa que el piso bajo de cada edificio se reserva a actividades relacionadas con la basura y el piso superior se dedica a la vivienda. Me parece increíble ver que estos montones y montones de basura son invisibles para la gente que vive allí, como este hombre tan distinguido que posa con toda esta basura desparramada detrás de él, o como estos dos hombres jóvenes que están sentados y charlando entre toneladas de basura. Mientras que para la mayoría de nosotros, vivir entre estos montones y montones de basura puede parecer totalmente inhabitable, para los del Zabbaleen, esto es un tipo diferente de normalidad. En todos estos lugares de los que he hablado hoy, lo que encuentro fascinante es que en realidad lo normal no existe, y esto prueba que la gente es capaz de adaptarse a cualquier tipo de situación. Durante el día, es bastante normal encontrarse con una pequeña celebración en la calle, como esta fiesta de compromiso. En esta tradición, la que pronto será la novia muestra todas sus pertenencias, que pronto entregará a su nuevo marido. Una reunión como esta ofrece tal yuxtaposición donde se muestra todo lo nuevo y se utiliza toda la basura como los útiles para la demostración de sus nuevos accesorios del hogar. Como Makoko y la Torre de David, por todo el Zabbaleen se pueden encontrar los mismos servicios que en cualquier vecindario público. Hay tiendas, cafés restaurantes, y la comunidad es esta comunidad de cristianos coptos, así que podrán encontrar una iglesia, incluido un gran número de iconografías religiosas por toda la zona, así como los servicios del día a día como las tiendas de reparación electrónica, los barberos, todo. La visita a las casas de los Zabbaleen está también llena de sorpresas. Mientras que desde el exterior, estas casas son como cualquier otra estructura informal de la ciudad, cuando uno entra, se encuentra con todo tipo de decisiones de diseño y de decoración de interiores. A pesar de las limitaciones de espacio y dinero, las casas de la zona están diseñadas con cuidado y detalle. Cada apartamento es único, y su individualidad cuenta la historia de las circunstancias y valores de cada familia. Muchos de ellos se toman muy en serio sus hogares y espacios interiores, y ponen en los detalles mucho trabajo y cuidado. Los espacios comunes también reciben la misma atención, en ellos las paredes se decoran con motivos de falso mármol. Pero a pesar de esta elaborada decoración, a veces estas viviendas reciben usos muy inesperados, como esta casa que me llamó la atención mientras que el barro y la hierba se salían literalmente por debajo la puerta de entrada. Cuando me invitaron a entrar, resulta que esta vivienda del quinto piso se estaba transformando completamente en una granja, en la que había seis o siete vacas pastando en lo que podría haber sido la sala de estar. Pues bien, en el apartamento frente al establo de vacas vive una pareja de recién casados en el que los vecinos describen como uno de los mejores apartamentos de la zona. La atención prestada a este detalle me asombró, y mientras que el dueño de la vivienda me guiaba orgulloso por el apartamento, de suelo a techo, cada elemento estaba decorado. Pero si no fuera por el olor nauseabundo, extrañamente familiar, que se filtra constantemente por el apartamento, sería fácil olvidar que uno está junto a un establo de vacas y encima de un vertedero. Lo que más me emocionó fue que a pesar de estas condiciones aparentemente inhóspitas, me dieron la bienvenida con los brazos abiertos a una casa hecha con amor, cuidado, y pasión ilimitada. Crucemos el mapa hasta China, a una zona llamada Shanxi, Henan y Gansu. En una región famosa por la tierra blanda y porosa de la meseta de Loess, vivían hasta hace poco unos 40 millones de personas en estas casas bajo tierra. Estas viviendas se llaman yaodongs. Por medio de esta arquitectura substractiva, estos yaodongs están construidos literalmente dentro de la tierra. En estos pueblos pueden ver un paisaje totalmente alterado, y oculto tras estos montículos de suelo y estas casas cuadradas, rectangulares localizadas a 7 metros bajo tierra. Cuando le pregunté a la gente por qué excavaban sus casas en la tierra, se limitaron a decirme que son malos cultivadores de trigo y de manzanas y que no tenían el dinero para comprar materiales, por lo que la excavación resultó ser la forma más lógica de vivir. De Makoko al Zabbaleen, estas comunidades se han planteado las tareas de planificación, diseño y gestión de las comunidades y vecindarios de varias formas que responden específicamente a su entorno y circunstancias. Creados por las personas que de verdad viven, trabajan y juegan en estos espacios concretos, estos vecindarios se han diseñado intuitivamente para sacarle el máximo partido a sus circunstancias. En la mayoría de estos lugares, la ausencia de gobierno es completa, dejando a los habitantes sin otra elección que recuperar materiales encontrados, y aunque estas comunidades están muy desfavorecidas, presentan verdaderos ejemplos de brillantes formas de ingenio, y demuestran que es cierto que tenemos la capacidad de adaptarnos a todo tipo de circunstancias. Lo hace que lugares como la Torre de David sean particularmente extraordinarios es esta especie de armazón-esqueleto que la gente utiliza como base que pueden aprovechar. Ahora, imaginen lo que estas comunidades tan ingeniosas podrían crear por sí mismas, y lo singulares que serían sus soluciones si se les proporcionaran infraestructuras básicas que pudieran aprovechar. Hoy en día se pueden ver esos grandes proyectos de complejos residenciales que ofrecen soluciones para la vivienda hechas en serie para un enorme número de personas. De China a Brasil, el propósito de estos proyectos es proporcionar tantas casas como sea posible, pero son totalmente genéricos y la verdad es que no son la solución a las necesidades individuales de la gente. Me gustaría terminar con una cita de una amiga mía y fuente de inspiración, Zita Cobb, la fundadora de la maravillosa Fundación Shorefast, con sede en la isla Fogo, en Terranova. Ella dice que "existe esta plaga de invariabilidad que está matando la alegría humana", y estoy totalmente de acuerdo con ella. Gracias. (Aplausos)